So we've established in principle
what the world's made out of from the
phenomenological or the
cybernetic or the narrative perspective
or the perspective of identity or the
perspective of
conscious experience or the perspective of
goal -directed pursuit that ties in with
the cybernetic and the phenomenological
approach and the basic idea that
is presented within those
systems but then in the narrative and
mythological representations of let's say our
frameworks of
reference is that the world as experienced
is made out of the domain of order which
is where
things that you want happen when you do
them and the domain of disorder which is
whenever anything
goes wrong and the domain of disorder
that's the domain of chaos in the
Taoist scheme that's the
domain of yin.
And the domain of order which is essentially
predictability right predictability in
relationship
to a goal that's a good way of thinking
about it it's a little more complicated than
that because
the fact that predictability exists say not
only indicates that you're on the way to
the goal
but it indicates that the principles by
which you're framing your perception so the
rules of
the game that you're playing are valid
right so it's got a twin meaning and that's
problematic
if you stumble or fail to move forward
because you don't know if it's a strategic
error which means
you just have to modify as we said yesterday
as we said previously you have to do a
normative
adjustment or if it's time serious time
for a new game and it's more significant
emotionally
when the game itself collapses because
everything that existed within that game now
becomes of
dubious
reality right certainly dubious validity
but also dubious reality is a hard thing to
distinguish
right because if your marriage falls apart
was the reality that you remembered when
it
was stable real or not or is that a failure
of a game it's very it's very difficult
to distinguish those things so
with this you step from the merely
abstract conceptual
world where we talk about things like
starting points and goals emotions and
motivations
tools and obstacles very practical
conceptualizations to the realm of symbolic
representation because what we're going
to discover and what we'll talk about in
this lecture in this sequence of lectures
is how the world we described yesterday is
represented
in narrative how it's characterized because
it's characterized and so now we have to
now we have to be introduced to
the characters once you understand
what the characters are what they
represent and how they're related to the
perceptual frame then
you have the key to understanding narrative
itself but more importantly than that
you have a key to understanding the deepest
of narratives which are the patterns of
narrative
the patterns of perception and direction
of attention and action that all stories
are based
on and that gives you access to a genuine
understanding of the religious domain now
you can do that if you're a religious
person if you're a convertible person if
you're a religious
describe the religious domain technically,
as far as I'm concerned, is that there
are tiers of
dependencies in our conceptualizations. So
we know this because sometimes you have a
shallow
conversation with someone, and sometimes
you have a deep conversation, and sometimes
something
shallow occurs in your life, and sometimes
something deep occurs. And so what does
that mean, shallow and deep? Well, a
profound experience changes the way you see
everything, right? That
can be a traumatic experience, but it
can be a very radically transforming
experience as well,
whereas a shallow experience requires a
minor adjustment, if any. And so that
implies the idea
that there's shallow and deep, which
we certainly understand in terms of
conversation, in terms of
story, in terms of art. The deeper a subject
is, the more other things depend on it,
right? So in a marriage,
typically, one of the fundamental
things is that you have to have a deep
conversation with someone, and that's what we
call a deep
conversation. So in a marriage, typically,
one of the fundamental principles that a
marriage depends on is the vow of
fidelity, right? It's what stabilizes the
interpretation of the interaction
and the environment. There's more than
that, but that's one of them. If that's
violated, that's a
profound challenge, because the entire
framework of interpretation that allows you
to specify the
meaning of everything that was involved
in the relationship, past, present, and
future,
falls, right? So that's a deep
problem. Now, you might say, how do
you account for the
elapse in a marriage, let's say, or a
betrayal in a relationship? Well, that's a
chaotic element,
but that's not a sufficient explanation,
because it's not merely chaotic, like your
car failing to
operate when you most need it. There is
an intent behind it, and the intent, the
chaotic intent,
has a motive. It has a motive. It has a
motive. It has a motive. It has a motive. It
has a motive.
There's a malevolent element to it, because
it's an immoral act, and so that domain
of chaos is not
only consists of what's unexpected, in its
deeper structures, it consists of what's
malevolent,
and that's important to note. If you're
a naive person, and you encounter your
own malevolence,
or someone else's, there's a reasonable
probability that you'll emerge traumatized,
which means your view of what,
human beings are, what you are, what
other people are, what safety is,
what danger you're in, all of that
transforms, and if you don't have a framework
within which to put
that, you're done. Then you're chronically
stressed enough, because everything's
falling
apart, and you don't know where you are,
so that you'll experience the neurological
devastation
that accompanies post -traumatic stress
disorder. Events that occur at a profound
enough level,
that's the religious level, and this is a
definition I'm putting forward. I'm not
asking you to believe anything.
There's a hierarchy of dependency. The closer
you get to the bottom, the more you're
starting to tread on sacred ground.
This is completely independent, in a way,
of your explicit religious beliefs. One of
the things I noticed in
my clinical practice,
was that people who had been really badly
hurt, which generally meant something
terrible had happened to
them, at the hands of
someone who intended for something horrible
to happen, even for them to discuss
those issues, they tended to lapse into
narrative structures that were religious
in connotation, because if you're hurt
very badly
at the hands of someone, including yourself,
who's intent on that damage, there
isn't a language other
than the language of good and evil that
encapsulates the phenomenon. There's no
other way of
telling the story. And so, well, you can
decide for yourself what that means with
regards to the
reality of such things. But this is a
technical description. Now, you could say, the
more profound
the principle that's violated by the
anomaly, the more destabilizing that is, so
that produces
negative emotion, but also the more promise
makes itself manifest, because there's
also the
possibility of a radical transformation.
And so, it's an ambivalent occurrence, but
it's also a
even if it's profoundly negative, you can
come out of an encounter with someone
malevolent a lot
wiser than you were. And
so, that's what it means
to get to the bottom of things.
Okay. So, we'll review briefly
what we mean by a frame of
perceptual reference, a perceptual frame,
a story. A Dasein, that's
the phenomenological term
from Heidegger, German. It means
something like the place of being.
So, that's his description of the
phenomenological frame. That's
the world as you experience it, right?
So, that's reality as it makes itself
manifest to the
conscious awareness. This is a
technical representation of that frame.
It is an attempt
to unite that vision with what we
know about the neuropsychology
of emotion. And so, that's the
definition of emotion. And we know a
lot. And so, this is a solid way of
representing it.
You're somewhere, you're trying to get
somewhere. You're goal -oriented in your
perceptions and your
actions and your intention. Your emotions,
your motivations feed into the goal and
into the
current state. Because, for example, if
you're hungry, the current state is that
you're hungry.
The desired state is that you're satiated,
right? The motivational state doesn't
just establish the
goal. It establishes the reference point
and determines your perceptions. When you
walk into
the kitchen, when you walk into the kitchen,
when you walk into the kitchen, when
you're
hungry, you see the world as a place to
procure food. That's what foregrounds out of
everything
else that you could be considering, right?
Okay, so what can happen along the way?
Well,
you can implement your plan properly, in
which case you proceed without incident
towards the goal,
in which case you satiate yourself. The
frame of reference flips, a new goal and a
new starting
point emerges, and that would be a new
episode in your day or in your life. Or
unexpected things could happen.
The fire alarm could go off. A burglar
could leap into the house. Something could
break.
Something could catch on fire. Or worse,
you know, people have heart attacks.
People get bad news on the phone and their
world falls apart. A tax form that is so
much trouble,
you can't imagine it, ends up in the mail
and you open it while you're downstairs
trying to
get something to eat. So what happens? Well,
we know that you see a pathway to your
destination.
You see the tools and obstacles that
would help you or interfere. You see the
friends of the foes
that would guide you on your way. You see
the agents of magical transformation. But
you see
things that are unexpected, too. That's
a anomaly. Now, the thing about what's
unexpected, this is a
very interesting thing to understand, is
that your perceptions bound the world so
that you take
everything there is, hyper -complicated,
and radically simplify it. You simplify it
by ignoring most of
it, right? Whenever you're doing one thing,
there's an infinite number of things
you're not taking
into account and you're not attending to.
Those things still exist, and they can pop
their ugly
little head up at any time, in any of
them, inside your frame of reference and
disrupt it.
That, I believe, is represented by the
eternal serpent in the garden. There's a
theological
question, right, in relationship to the
narrative that begins Genesis, which is,
why would God create a garden and put a
snake in it? The answer to that seems to be
something like,
no gardens without snakes. It's not
possible, right? Because to make a partial
enclosure,
you have to exclude. But the exclusion is
imperfect, and it can always come welling
back up.
You could protect your children, but that
doesn't mean they won't get access to
someone's phone and
fall into the world of violent pornography,
right? And that's, believe me, that's
the world's welling its way back into the
walled garden. That's what paradise is.
By the way, a walled garden that you're
trying to create that produces security and
an optimally
playful, adventurous place that has
everything that's malevolent and terrible
excluded,
right? And so every place you go has that
possibility of the unexpected and the
anomalous.
And so partly what you want to do is you
want to master how you operate in any given
game.
But more importantly, you
have to operate in the space
between games or in the space that is composed
of those events that transform games.
You can think
about that as a metagame. What's the problem?
How do you do what you know you should
do? Well,
that's a problem. How do you act when you
don't know what's going on? That's a very
different
problem. Now, if you can solve that second
problem as well as the first problem,
then you're at home
on explored territory and
you're at home in the space.
Unexplored territory. And since the world
is made out of order, which is explored
territory,
which is the territory that you inhabit
when things are going according to plan,
the world's composed of that and unexplored
territory, chaos, right? The domain of
the
unknown and the anomalous. If you can master
both of those, then you're at home in
the world. Now,
that's the most meaningful path of being
because your emotions are actually
optimized when you're
practicing both. So if you're playing a
game, for example, with a partner, with a
team,
the game is optimally engaging when
it's going according to plan, which is
everyone's playing
by the rules and everyone is aiming for
the goal, which so the game has the same
structure as the
phenomenological frame, right? Everyone's
aiming at the goal, right? You want to be
engaged in the game in a manner that
ensures that it lays itself out
predictably,
but you want to be pushing yourself
to your limits on the edge of chaos
so that while you master the
skills that are at hand in the game,
you're also expanding your repertoire of
skills.
And that's when the game will be maximally
engaging. It doesn't matter what you're
doing.
It doesn't matter what the frame is. That
holds constant, right? If you're bored,
but you're not going to be bored, you're
going to be bored. And that's when you're
going to be
an enterprise, your attitude towards it
is wrong, right? You haven't, you haven't
got the thing.
You haven't got the lens that you're
using to examine the phenomenon
optimized because if you did, then it
would grip you. And so you can change what
you're looking at.
That's the typical pattern of people who at
least are willing to change, but you can
also change the
way you're looking at what you're looking
at. One of the things I learned, for
example, in my clinical practice,
this is that if I started, if my attention
started to drift when I was speaking with
one of my
clients, so what happens then? So like,
let's say my goal is to communicate with you
towards an end
and the end would be the exchange of
information so that you emerge more integrated.
And perhaps
I learned something along the way. Okay.
So that's the, you could say that's the
therapeutic frame.
We're working in what
we mutually agree to be
our mutual best interests. We've established
that by negotiation. If I'm listening
to your account
of your problems, your starting place and
your goal, and my attention drifts, what's
happening
is that that frame is being, is being
challenged by other frames of reference that
my attention is
toying with, right? These other motivational
states that might be one of the things
I noticed, for example, is I hated
to start a clinical episode.
If there was something wrong with my computer,
because when there's something wrong
with my computer, it makes me obsessive
till I fix it. And so if a client had to be
misfortunate enough,
unfortunate enough to come in, just when
I was dealing with some idiot computer
problem,
I would flip continually. It was I'd
listen. And then I think about the computer
problem,
but so you can see when you're listening to
someone that there'll be competition for
the way you're framing the,
your attention, right? Um,
that can cause you a lot of trouble on
a date, for example, that particular
phenomenon.
So in any case, what I learned
was that if the conversation
I was having with my client wasn't
sufficiently engaging to chase away competing
frames, then I wasn't listening hard
enough.
I wasn't paying enough attention, right?
And attention has this, the, the,
the, the Egyptians,
the ancient Egyptians, they
worshiped attention. They believed
it was the highest God, their God, Horus.
Horus is the eye, the famous Egyptian eye
with the open
pupil. Horus was also a Falcon. And the
reason Horus was like Zazu in the lion King
who could
fly up and see everything from a height.
He was the eyes of the King. Horus is the
open
eyes of the King. That's another mythological
representation in ancient Egypt. The
Egyptians
determined that attention was the revivifying
spirit of the dormant or pathological
state.
And they worshiped that as the highest
God, the open eye, the ability to pay
attention and
attention. See attention oriented upward
is really indistinguishable from love.
That's a good, that's
another good thing to know. That's why
children are so desperate. Everyone, by the
way, children
are so desperate for love. Attention is a
currency. All the corporations fight for
it, right? So
attention is, you could say in a way that
attention is the foundation of the world.
That's, that's not
an overstatement.
It's a very much worth knowing. And the
focus of attention has a revivifying
quality. One of the
things you'll notice if you ever get a new
apartment or a new house is that any part
of the
house that you haven't
attended to, cleaned,
ordered, deeply observed, it's not yours.
It'll still feel, you know, there's a
difference between a house and a home.
The difference is attention. A home is a
house where everything has been attended
to.
And that turns it from chaotic possibility
that's alienating into territory that's
secure and a
place of play, right? And everything works
on that principle. So attention. All
right. So now, how do
you pay attention to what you don't understand?
That's a complicated problem. How do
you deal with
what you can't comprehend? That's a
complicated problem. It seems impossible in a
sense, right? It seems counterintuitive.
That that could even be a possibility. But
if the world is made out of chaos, order
where things are
secure, maybe a bit dull. If it's made out
of order and chaos, then you need to be
able to maneuver in
both. But chaos by its definition is
unstructured and incomprehensible. So
how is it that you can
adopt a stance towards it that works? That
is essentially the religious problem. And
you can imagine why. It's
the world's made out of chaos and order.
The deepest problem is obviously how you
deal with chaos and order.
Now here, and you might think, well,
that's all well and good, but it's merely
symbolic. It's like,
we're going to find out.
It's not merely symbolic. Your brain
has two hemispheres, right? And one is
specialized for order, and the other is
specialized for chaos. And that's a
biological mechanism that evolved. And the
selection mechanism for
evolution, that's reality.
And so if reality has selected us to
have a bicameral consciousness, which is
the case, then how in the world can you
state that the attributes to which those
hemispheres are adapted aren't real?
It's the very definition
of real. Real is what
selects. Real is what kills you. Real is
what allows you to live if you do it right.
Right? That's real. And that
bifurcated consciousness doesn't
only seem to be a necessary mechanism of
living nervous systems. Even artificial
networks appear to need
a module that maintains
stability, and a module that deals
with exceptions. Right? If you
meld them, the systematic
element collapses. And
there's a
famous example of this. I can't
remember where I read it.
There's a famous example of this.
I can't remember where I read it.
About it or concrete and as of yet
undetermined that's what you face
in the morning right you
wake up in your orderly environment but
that's not what you face you don't pay
attention to your
covers in your bed i mean you might want
to make it but but the concerns that make
themselves
manifest to your consciousness are the
possibilities of the day and that might be
overwhelming
especially if you're depressed or
anxious too much too much chaos too much
unstructured possibility
optimally you'd be raring to go because
you could see the treasure in the dragon
but your
consciousness your consciousness
concentrates on what has not yet been
formalized and that's the
spirit that creates the world that's the
image of god in man and woman you're
moving from where
you are to where you are to where you are
to where you are to where you are to where
you are to
where you deem better right that's an upward
movement you see the phenomena that we
described
yesterday the tools obstacles the friends
and foes etc and there's the rabbit hole
the unpredicted event and so we're going to
delve into that to see more particularly
what it
means to fall down that rabbit hole
what's in there but also to understand as
well and
these things have to be done in parallel
how one game is related to another okay so
what are i'll
give you an example of this in literature
you know the quidditch game in harry
potter it's a
weird game right because two things are
happening at the same time there's the
ordinary team playing
an ordinary game which is basically soccer
basketball just a typical game which is
hit
the target right collectively according
to a set of principles that's a game but
there's a
metagame going on and that's a game that's
a game that's a game that's a game that's
a game
going on at the same time remember the
seekers play that the seekers play that right
so that is
the game that seekers play it's not the
ordinary game it's a game on top of a game
or it's a game
underneath the game that's foundational
it's more crucial it's more real now if in
the quidditch arrangement if the
seeker catches the snitch then they
get a usually enough points to
win the whole game so that's
now the snitch is a very weird thing it's
a gold ball with wings now it turns out
that that's a
representation of an alchemical symbol
called the round chaos and the round chaos
was regarded by
the alchemist as the container of primordial
matter of reality itself and so the
seeker
who wins the game is the person who pays
enough attention to find the container of
what's ultimate it's exactly
what happens to moses in the
garden with the burning bush he pays attention
and then more attention and then more
attention and
he gets right to the bottom of something
and that's when the divine reveals itself
and
transforms his character he he moves from
shepherd to leader right then he can speak
truth to power
and he can lead the slaves to the promised
land and define the promised land and
speak in a manner
that's compelling such that people will
listen and tell the stories that motivate
right because
he's taken something from the garden with
the burning bush and he's taken something
from the
garden with the burning bush and he's taken
something from the burning bush and he's
taken something from the burning bush and
he's taken something from the burning bush
and he's taken something from the burning
bush and he's taken something from the
burning bush and he's taken something from
the burning bush and he's taken something
from the burning bush and he's taken something
from the burning bush and he's taken
something from the burning bush and he's
taken something from the burning bush and
he's taken something from the burning bush
and he's taken something from the burning
bush and he's taken something from the
burning bush and he's taken something from
the burning bush and he's taken something
from the burning bush and he's taken
something from the burning bush and he's
taken something from the burning bush and
he's taken something from the burning bush
and he's taken something from the burning
bush and he's taken something from the
burning bush and he's taken something from
the burning bush and he's taken something
from the burning bush and he's taken
something from the burning bush and he's
taken something from the burning bush
ability as a specialist expands because
everything is associated with the complexity
of everything
else the more you study one thing the
more you see how it's connected to other
things and then
other things and then other things and then
other things and that's how you get to
the bottom of
things and so you can achieve wisdom this
is a useful thing to know too you can
achieve wisdom
through any upward aiming disciplinary
pursuit and so it doesn't really matter what
calls to you
and there'll be idiosyncrasies in that
you won't be interested in the same thing
that you'll be
interested in and you might think well
even though the interest is the same the
target is different
but not exactly because you could say that
the ground of being is attempting to make
itself
manifest through all of its proximal
manifestations right and if you pay enough
attention you'd figure
that out so that's very much worth knowing
and so a call can come to you that'll be
something that grips your
interest now you have to have
sorted yourself out well enough so that
you're not being drawing this drawn to
something
pathological because your aim is misaligned
but given that if something calls to you
or bothers
you at the level of conscience if you take
it with sufficient seriousness and pursue
it then
it'll lead you to the bottom of things
right so that's very much worth knowing get
great at one
thing and that'll generalize and so that's
that's that that's an apprenticeship
right that's an
apprenticeship right and you
merge from an apprenticeship as a master
right you have a masterpiece and that
signifies that
you're now maybe even capable of transforming
the discipline that you've apprenticed
within right right so but you have to
subjugate yourself first that's really what
socialization is and so
it's a narrowing and then a broadening and
but there's no second broadening without
that initial focus focus focused
attention okay something unpredictable
just works but it's not always the first
thing that happens disinhibition of emotion
right you
encounter this realm of novelty that's
yin that's chaos it's all that which
exists outside the frame
that you've been inhabiting it could be
the universe of all potentially playable
games
that's a good way of thinking about it so
for better or for worse down the rabbit
hole
disinhibited emotion and motivation why
because you don't know what to do so what
does your body do
prepare to do and you're not going to get
away with it right you're going to have to
go to the Everything. And that puts you on
edge and ready. But in doses that are too
overwhelming, it's physiologically
devastating. Right. So you have to
contend with that so that you can benefit
from that state of preparation without
exhausting yourself.
All right. If the rabbit
hole is sufficiently
deep, if the unexpected thing that
emerges is sufficiently problematic,
that all your pathways forward are
blocked, then what? Then you die?
Or is it time for a new game? This is the
thing that's so remarkable about human
beings. You know, it's not an
overstatement to say that an animal who
has all its pathways
forward blocked will die.
A human being who has all...
All his pathways forward blocked will
find a new aim. Right. That's a radical
transformation. That's a creative
transformation. Time for a new game. Well, what
does that mean? It means time for a new
story. It means time for a new world. It
means time for a new character. It means
time for a new spirit. Right. A new
pathway. New friends. New foes. Everything
transforms. Right. But you can do that.
You can become a new person. This is
represented fairly consistently in the Old
Testament.
You see this in particular in the story
of Abraham. He undergoes a series of
transformative adventures. Right. And so
they would be different frames or different
games and cruise skill like you do in a
video game with each adventure until he
transforms so completely
God grants him a new name.
Same thing happens with Jacob who becomes
Israel. So the idea is that if you climb
Jacob's ladder in this succession of
adventures, you can transform your character.
Character so completely that it's
as if you become a new person.
Right. And that's well, and then what
person should you try to become?
Well, our initial hypothesis is one
who's the master of order and chaos.
Right. So that's the question.
How do you do that down the rabbit hole?
Why is it chaos?
Well, because if your pathway is blocked
forward sufficiently, so the game is in
question, everything's up in the air.
The one of the mythological
representations of that.
Interestingly enough, Mircea Eliade, a
Romanian historian of religion, documents
this extraordinarily well, particularly in
a book called The Sacred and the Profane.
Every collapse is a return
to the beginning of time.
Now, this gives you a notion of what the
beginning means in the narrative frame.
The Genesis beginning isn't the
scientific materialist beginning.
It's how everything begins.
It's the beginning of everything.
It's the beginning in the past.
It's the beginning now, and it's
the beginning in the future.
It's how everything emerges out of chaos.
That's the word of God floating
on the primordial waters.
The primordial waters are a
very common symbol of chaos.
Why? You don't know what's in the water.
Right. Dark water, deep
water, sharks, carnivores.
Right. The unknown place that you
can draw things up from the depths.
At a deeper level, the place
where life itself emerged.
Right. So the primordial
waters are the birthplace.
An intermediary birthplace of the
world is such the spirit of God that
rests on the water, broods on the water,
dwells on the water is the ordering
principle that confronts
possibility and casts
it into order.
More specifically, the injunction in the
Genesis text is not only into order,
but the order that's good or very good.
So that begs a question, too, which is
what does your aim have to be to encounter
the realm of possibility in a manner
that's meaningful in a way that transforms
that possibility into
what's good or very good?
There's an aim that is a precondition
for that magical process.
That in Christianity, that question
took thousands of years to answer
because it wasn't.
It wasn't really answered until the gospel
account in John, where John posited that
the spirit of voluntary, ultimate
voluntary self -sacrifice, that's
Christ,
was the same spirit that operates
at the beginning of things.
If what's extracted from possibility
is the order that's good or very good.
So what would that mean?
Well, you can think about it concretely.
How much love should you
have for your children?
If you wanted to situate them optimally,
would you lay your life down for
them in principle or in reality?
Well, the answer to that has to be yes.
And so to establish the most profound
relationship with someone in the attempt
to make that relationship
everything it could be, you bring
everything to bear.
Everything.
And so that's the spirit that has to
exist at the beginning of things.
And that's what's going to be the basis
for what emerges to be good or very good.
Right. You can imagine encountering it
with the spirit of power and what would be
extracted in consequence of that,
or the spirit of hedonistic self,
immediate hedonistic self-gratification.
Those are two very common competing
spirits, you might say, or the spirit
of hopelessness and nihilism.
You're going to extract very different
forms of order in consequence of your
aim.
Right.
So aim up. That's the rule.
Aim up.
That begs the question,
what do you mean by up?
Right. Well, at minimum, you
mean not toward the abyss.
At minimum, you mean that.
Okay. So your pathway is blocked.
It's time for a new game.
So everything is made new again.
That's a reversion to the state of
possibility that exists at the beginning.
It's not exactly the beginning of time.
It's D.
It's a deeper notion of
beginning than that.
The beginning of everything.
Everything collapses into possibility.
That's that can freeze
you with apprehension.
That's the kids in the Harry Potter second
volume who encounter the basilisk
that is the great serpent.
That's another symbol of chaos that lurks
under everything, which is why it's in
the pipes under the magical castle.
It's the it's the unstable chaos.
The chaos that makes
itself suddenly present in
in all imaginable circumstances.
It's always there as a
possibility right now.
You remember that Harry determines
to go into its lair. Right.
And so that's a hint about the
appropriate pathway to take to master the
chaotic domain.
Okay. So now it's out of this game.
That's the collapse of a relationship.
That's probably where people experience.
That most self evidently in ordinary life.
Right. Because you orient yourself
to a large degree around a set
of fundamental relationships.
And when they collapse,
then well, then what?
Then where are you? Then who are you?
Then what do you make of your past?
But also what new possibilities
does that open up for the future?
Well, those are the questions that emerge
and the instinctive reaction to that is.
Preparation for all things.
Right. Okay.
That's a beginning story, right?
That's the story of the fall.
So the way that history begins in the
biblical accounts is that Adam and Eve
incorporate something
that they were, you say,
where there was a strong
suggestion that they
forswear from that endeavor.
What does that mean?
It means they bit off more
than they could chew.
Right. So there's a there's
an issue there of pride.
You want to encounter
something that's challenging.
You want to encounter what's unknown.
But you don't want to prematurely claim
that you're the master of all things and
then attempt to establish the
preconditions of the moral order itself.
And that's what Satan,
that's that chaos dragon.
That's the temptation
that's put forward to Eve.
She bites off more than she can chew.
Then Adam bites off more than he can chew.
And that's a sin of pride and usurpation.
And that's the fall.
That's when history begins
in the biblical sense.
And so what does that mean for?
And that's the that's the land of toil
and trouble and thorns and
thistles and things that go wrong.
Well, why?
Prideful misalignment turns the world
from paradise to the place of fallen man.
That's right. That's right.
That's right.
So that's that's a
that's an anomaly story.
Like the serpent is the prime symbolic
representation of the deepest of anomalies.
Why? Why a serpent?
Why a reptile?
Well, human beings have been mammals have
been fighting with reptiles for 100
million years, a very long time.
Wherever there are primates and
poisonous camouflaged serpents,
the primates have more acute vision.
Right. You remember in the Genesis story
that the snake provides
Adam and Eve with vision.
Right. We're also very good, by the way,
at seeing camouflaged patterns in
the lower half of our visual system.
We're better at that
than in the upper half.
Why? Well, most snakes are on the ground.
Right. So snakes definitely
sharpened our vision.
So we've been in a battle
with a battle with what?
What is the serpent represent?
Definitely a predator. Right.
But also an inhuman predator, a predator
that you can't make contact with.
Like a Komodo dragon is a more
terrifying entity even than a tiger.
Because a tiger, you
can kind of understand.
But a Komodo dragon, it's
like you're not you.
It's not it's a lot more that
you're not merely the same species.
Right. And poisonous snakes have been
a formidable enemy of primates and of
mankind for a very long period of time.
Our earliest tree dwelling relatives were
preyed upon. What's a dragon?
Preyed upon by birds of the air.
That's the wings by
serpents of the ground.
That's the scales by fire.
Well, why? Well, what's a threat
if you're a tree dwelling?
Primate fire. Right.
What's a dragon winged,
clawed, fire breathing bird?
Right. So the dragon idea is the
idea of dangerous predator itself.
It's an amalgam.
Predator is lion, tiger,
bear, Komodo, dragon, shark.
That's a strange category, right?
Because there's no features in
common across those animals,
apart from the fact that they'll eat you,
which turns out to be a very cardinal
reason for the categorization. Dragon is
the imagistic equivalent of the concept
of predator. Right.
And so and that's a deep rabbit hole as
well, because you might say that there are
few anomalies.
More compelling than a predator.
But then that begs the question as well.
What is the worst of
all possible predators?
There's a strange emergent idea that
develops, as I said, over thousands of
years from the foundation
of the Genesis narrative.
The fall Eve is tempted by a snake, but
that snake is represented eventually as
Satan.
Well, why?
Well, what's the worst predator?
Thing? Thing that'll eat you.
Thing that'll poison you.
Thing that'll poison your heart.
The serpent in the heart of your
enemy, the serpent in your own heart.
Right. So those are steps of predation.
Right. And those are what you say.
They're investigations into the depths
of what it is that poses the most
fundamental threat.
The great catastrophes of the 20th
century were not caused by predators,
not of the natural kind.
They were caused by what?
Spiritual predators.
Okay. Was that the Nazis or was that the
weakness in the hearts of people that
allowed that spirit to possess
a nation and then the world?
Same question applies
on the communist front.
And that means if it's the weakness in
the hearts of the people who allowed
themselves to be possessed, and that
happened to virtually everyone,
then what does that mean about
you and your capability to
withstand that temptation
if it comes along?
So that would be the temptation of power,
let's say, or a kind of usurping nihilism
in the case of the bloody communists.
And so what is the most profound
manifestation of chaos?
That's a religious question.
And the answer to that is it's an answer
that Milton Dante attempted
to provide in a poetic form.
It's like, what's the horror that's
at the bottom of the worst horror?
For Dante, as I said yesterday,
it was betrayal, right?
Because that's the inversion
of love for Milton.
It was the usurping quality of
the prideful intellect, right?
And so those are characterizations
of the spirit that rules over hell.
And what's hell?
The frame that aims down or the structure
of the frames that aim down to the lowest
possible point, which is the bottomless
pit. Hell, right.
And that's an eternal place, too, because
it's first of all, if you're there,
then it feels eternal, but
it's always there as a it's
always there as a possibility.
It's a possibility.
It's always under things.
That's another way of thinking about it.
You know, it's small.
This is this is this is being observed
when countries, when societies go wildly
astray. You know, the pathway
to perdition is a multitude.
Very small sins, usually
avoidance, usually stepping back.
Now, you might be called upon to resist
the transformations in an
ideological direction.
And to fail to do that merely
means that you turn a blind eye.
And every time you do that,
it seems like nothing.
It seems like the safe thing to do, the
secure thing to do, the sensible thing to
do. But one step at a time.
You end up somewhere you
seriously don't want to be.
And so the question that begs is how
much attention should you be paying?
Well, there's an insistence that the
spirit that dwelled on the water when the
order that was good emerged was not only
love, but the truth that will set you free.
So what does that imply?
It implies that and the
word that's the logos.
The word incarnate is
the spirit that dwells
on the water properly at the
beginning of all things.
What's the word?
Certainly the truth
that will set you free.
What does that mean?
Don't state falsehoods.
Right. Because you you know this.
It has to be true.
If you're trying to produce a reality
that's robust as a consequence of your
encounter with chaos and you cast
falsehoods on the water, you'll produce
a reality that's false, obviously.
And how can a reality that's false
stand?
It's preposterous.
You build something alongside something
you know to be true and take shelter in
that. How is that going to work?
Well, temporarily.
And so why do people lie to get something
they don't deserve now and to avoid
something they do deserve now?
And it's a bad medium
to long term strategy.
Here's a definition of faith.
Faith is the proposition that whatever
happens, if you state the truth, is the
best thing that could happen no matter
what it looks like to you, right,
that's a foundational determination.
Are you going to have faith in the truth?
What does that mean?
It means exactly what I just said.
So that's the underlying
structure of a story.
It's this collapse into chaos that in
any adventure story, in any romance,
you see the the emergence of a stable state
to begin with and then the introduction
of a complex problem and
the complex problem.
It requires a magical transformation.
Otherwise, the story has no depth.
The deeper the transformation.
So the more levels of upward endeavor
involved, the more profound the story.
And so a shallow story would involve
a transformation that's sort
of at hand for everyone.
And a deep story would involve a
transformation that remakes the character
so completely that it's as if
they're another person, right?
And it's much harder
to enjoy, I would say,
a deep narrative like that.
It requires serious
attention and contemplation.
So it's much more than
mere light entertainment.
But even if it's merely light
entertainment, which means it does engage
you, it inevitably
portrays a transformation.
And you can see that happening
in a romantic adventure where
someone has a relationship and
because of their own character,
illogical faults or bad luck, things fall
apart and they're in a state of disarray.
And then.
They find someone new and to attract that
person, they have to make changes to how
they relate to the world and
they grow in consequence.
And, you know, they come together
and they live happily ever after.
And that's a romantic comedy.
And an adventure story has the same
structure, although in the tool
and obstacle world, you could say instead
of in the relational world and the tool
and obstacle world, by the way, that's the
world that men are more comfortable in
and more particularly enjoy inhabiting.
And the relational world is the world that
women are more likely to be interested
in.
Interest is the biggest differentiator
between men and women that we know.
Women are more interested
in people than men are.
On average, it's quite a large difference.
And men are more interested in things.
And that's quite a large difference.
There's echoes of that in chimpanzees.
Even you can see some sex differentiation
and toy choice, for example, among
chimpanzees.
So it's a deep division.
And so and the world of adventure,
that's a world that has more to do
with, well, the tool obstacle world.
Now, if you have a extremely well-balanced
narrative, you have a romantic adventure.
And that's a good way of contemplating
the proper structure of your life.
Instead, if you're fortunate, ultimately
fortunate, then it's a romantic adventure.
Right. And that's a challenge.
It's a challenge on the social
front to keep the romance alive.
It's a challenge on the tool and obstacle
front to keep the adventure moving
forward.
Right. You have to dance
attentively to make that happen.
Right. And the reward will be a
life that's rich and meaningful.
That's an echo of life eternal.
And if you embody that
pattern optimally, then you
trod the path of Abraham
and become the embodiment of the
spirit of the father of nations.
If you're a man. That's right.
That's right.
This is a complicated idea.
When things collapse,
what collapses exactly?
And what's the how do you characterize
the potential that remains?
Well, I attempted to portray
in this diagram that anomaly
even demolishes the boundary
between spirit and matter.
What do I mean by that?
See, if you encounter a new situation, a
new person, a new set of circumstances,
you don't know what's going on, and
so there's an inchoate, unstructured
possibility in front of you.
And then what you do is you divide that
into spirit and world matter, let's say, or
what matters for that matter.
Why?
When you establish a relationship
with someone, you learn who they are.
So let's call that the material side, so
to speak, because you're learning about
something external to you.
Or if you investigate a complex piece of
machinery, you learn about the machinery,
but you also learn about yourself.
And so in that encounter with something
new, you pull out spirit, which is
personality,
and you expand and develop that, and then
you also generate the world around that.
And so a deep enough anomaly
intermingles them so that what you're
encountering is the possibility of a
new world that you could establish in
consequence
of investigation and transformation, but
also a new you, a new value structure.
So psyche and matter are extracted from
something more primordial, which is this
realm of possibility, which is the
intermingling of everything
that makes itself manifest to you when
your provisional frame collapses.
Right.
OK, so let's simplify this to some degree.
I tried to show here how the
object transforms with the frame.
So I think the best way to think about
an object, apart from tool and obstacle,
let's say, is that an object, let's say
a tool, something that you sit on like
the chair, is something that has a
penumbra of possibility around it.
So I used the beer bottle
example yesterday.
You can stand on that chair
and use it as a ladder, right?
You can use it as a prop in a play.
You can take it apart.
This is what Pinocchio does
in the belly of the whale.
You can take it apart and build a fire,
and that helps you escape from the dragon,
which is obviously what fire did for us,
by the way, since it kept the predators
at bay, and Pinocchio was a master
of fire in that representation.
And that's what freed him
from the belly of the whale.
So,
the phenomenon, the chair, whatever
it is that you're apprehending,
has the function that's specified by
your aim and a wealth of potential
possibilities around it, and
that's all part of the object.
OK, so how might you construe this?
Well, imagine I said the
thing in itself there.
Imagine that that's an
orchard viewed from the air.
OK, so how do you represent that?
Well, the simplest representation,
is object one, right?
It's a rectangle.
That's a pretty useful representation.
If you want to know how to go
around the orchard, right?
You saw when Google Maps started to
map out the world, its initial maps of
buildings, of places were empty squares,
right? And the detail fills in, right?
You see icons, you see low resolution
representations of what's there.
That's why you can watch
The Simpsons or South Park.
It's primitive animation.
Everything's circles and squares
moving the way people move.
That's enough.
It's a placeholder for reality.
Your object perceptions
are like that, too, right?
They're icons.
I only see the front of you, right?
I can't see beneath the surface.
I certainly can't see down
into your molecular structure.
I can't see up into the social
structures that you're a part of.
You're a thin slice
in time and in space.
And very much perspectivized.
And so is that real?
You know, one of the things Picasso was
doing with those strange paintings of
people from the front and the side?
Well, his hypothesis was that that's
more real, because there you are.
Don't move your head.
And there you are.
And why wouldn't I paint
both of those at once?
If I was trying to portray you, what
makes the head on vision more real?
It's less real, right?
So there's many ways to look at something.
Well, I laid some out here, right?
The simplest one is a square.
If you wanted to zoom in and adopt
a higher resolution representation,
you can represent four squares or four
rectangles with pathways through them.
Or an even higher resolution
representation is object three.
That would enable you to plot a
trajectory through the trees, right?
The object four is an amalgam of one and
two, and then object five is almost as high
resolution as this
so-called thing in itself.
Why would you use an icon?
Look, if you're doing graphic work on a
computer, do you use the highest resolution
file? No, you use the lowest resolution
file that works for your purposes.
Right. That's exactly
how perception works.
You use the lowest resolution
representation that suits your purposes.
Here's proof.
There's a series of
experiments that were done.
They started at Harvard.
Dan Simon was the professor who was
integrally involved in this research,
although he didn't establish the field,
if I remember correctly.
So here's an experiment.
You're walking through a
university campus as a tourist.
OK, and an undergraduate comes up to you
with a map and asks you for directions.
All right. So you start interacting.
While you're doing that, workmen
who are relatively rude come
walking between you with a
door. There's two of them.
The person you're talking
to grabs the door.
You don't see him because the door is.
Here he continues.
And one of the people holding the door
takes the map and keeps talking to you.
Seventy percent of the people
don't notice the switch.
Right. Here's another experiment.
Why? All undergraduates who are asking
for directions in the university
yard are interchangeable.
Why? Because you don't
need to know anything
about them apart from what's
relevant to the task at hand.
You don't even see it.
Here's another famous experiment.
There's three people dressed
in black and there's three people dressed
in white and they're playing basketball,
bouncing a basketball between them, the
black dressed people to the black people,
the white dressed people
to the white people.
Your job is to count how many times the
white people bounce and pass
or throw the basketball.
You have about forty five seconds.
You do that during this.
Now, so these people fill the
screen, the video screen.
OK, it's not a distance shot.
Everyone's clear.
Well, that happens.
A man dressed in a gorilla suit
comes right into the middle
of the camera and beats his chest
for five seconds and then leaves.
Seventy, eighty percent of the
people don't see the gorilla.
Why? Because you see what's
relevant to your aim.
And so that's change blindness.
There's a whole perceptual field
that studies change blindness.
How opaque we are to the
transformations of the world.
So what's what do you see?
You see any change that interferes
with what you're doing.
Right, right. So that's what
you become conscious of.
So the pathway you walk, the things
that you use or that interfere at hand.
If something emerges that is
an impediment, you see it.
Otherwise it's invisible.
And I would recommend
you can consider this.
Go online, try some of these
change blindness experiments.
You will not believe how blind you are and
learning that's extremely useful because
the question when you're in trouble
always is, what am I missing?
Right. What presuppositions led me here?
What do I have to shed or sacrifice to
transform my viewpoint in this situation?
Right. What am I not attending?
An infinite landscape of possibility.
Right now.
So that's a compression of reality into the
icon and into the absolutely invisible.
That's how we simplify the world so that
we can exist in it with our limited
capacity.
That's our comprehension. A word
is a second order compression.
So object one rectangle.
So what does rectangle mean?
Rectangle is a sound that
represents an icon of a phenomena.
Right. And so when I speak,
what happens in the background of your
imagination is the word is unpacked
into the icon that represents the
thing. That's how we communicate.
Right. And, you know, I don't know if this
has happened to you. When I was a kid,
and I would read fiction, I could really
see the characters in my imagination.
And I was often less than thrilled when I
went to a movie because the characters
didn't match my imagination.
As I got older and kept reading fiction,
although I did less and less of that
as I got older, I found that my
imagination had almost ceased. I just
read and I could still understand.
And I think it was because
I had automatized the image
comprehension so completely
that it became unconscious.
I was just reading directly from the words
with no intermediary of imagination.
Gain and efficiency, a loss
in richness of experience.
Very frequently the case
with gain and efficiency.
So that's how we compress
the world to communicate.
Right. The world's complex.
Compress it into an icon,
a tile, a placeholder.
The simplest representation
that suffices for the task.
Right. It's computationally less intense.
That's why you use thumbnails on a computer
instead of full resolution images.
You don't need them. The
detail is irrelevant.
Well, why is the detail irrelevant?
Because you can get where you want
to go with a simpler representation.
And you certainly want that.
A word simplifies even more, right?
Compresses the world even more.
And so there's real power in that because
you can refer to so many things
with words that aren't there.
But obviously,
the reality that's portrayed by the words
is less rich than the reality that would
be portrayed by an image or certainly
by the phenomena in question.
There's images that I'm going to show you
that have literally taken
thousands of years to unpack.
There's so much information
in one image that it's
almost inexhaustible.
And of course, the thing that represents
is far more inexhaustible than that.